<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>audio on Recent posts</title><link>https://blog.johnnovak.net/tags/audio/</link><description>Recent content in audio on Recent posts</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.johnnovak.net/tags/audio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Grand MS-DOS gaming General MIDI showdown</title><link>https://blog.johnnovak.net/2023/03/05/grand-ms-dos-gaming-general-midi-showdown/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.johnnovak.net/2023/03/05/grand-ms-dos-gaming-general-midi-showdown/</guid><description>Table of contents Introduction Meet the contestants Roland Sound Canvas SC-55 Roland Sound Canvas VA Yamaha MU80 Yamaha S-YXG50 Recording process Capturing MIDI data Recording the audio Post-processing Recordings Quick impressions Final verdict Roland SC-55 vs Roland Sound Canvas VA Roland SC-55 vs later Sound Canvas models Roland SC-55 vs Yamaha MU80 Yamaha MU80 vs Yamaha S-YXG50 In closing Recordings, links &amp;amp; further reading Files Softsynths Reviews Introduction The Roland SC-55 sound module is the undisputed king of mid-late 90s General MIDI music in MS-DOS retro gaming circles.</description></item><item><title>Creating a Nim wrapper for FMOD</title><link>https://blog.johnnovak.net/2018/07/07/creating-a-nim-wrapper-for-fmod/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.johnnovak.net/2018/07/07/creating-a-nim-wrapper-for-fmod/</guid><description>Table of contents Overview Prerequisites Auto-generating the basic wrapper Fixing conversion errors &amp;ndash; Part 1 Opaqueue C structs Circular types Unsigned integer literals Dynamic linking Fixing conversion errors &amp;mdash; Part 2 FMOD callbacks and function pointers Missing constants Error handling helpers Improving the wrapper Conclusion Further links of interest Overview One of the many attractive things about Nim is its ability to interface with C libraries relatively easily, be they either statically linked or dynamically loaded.</description></item></channel></rss>