<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>rant on Recent posts</title><link>https://blog.johnnovak.net/tags/rant/</link><description>Recent content in rant on Recent posts</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.johnnovak.net/tags/rant/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cross-platform GUI Toolkit Trainwreck --- 2016 Edition</title><link>https://blog.johnnovak.net/cross-platform-gui-toolkit-trainwreck-2016-edition/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.johnnovak.net/cross-platform-gui-toolkit-trainwreck-2016-edition/</guid><description>Ok, I&amp;rsquo;m not too sure in what direction this post will go, an informative article, a rant, or both. Probably a bit of both, with an emphasis on the rant part, given my current not-quite-positive emotional involvement with the topic. Gentlemen (and gentlewomen), please fasten your seatbelts!
UPDATE #1: It turned out to be a quite informative mega-post in the end, just don&amp;rsquo;t give up reading after the first section&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>The quest for a programming language that doesn't suck --- Part 1</title><link>https://blog.johnnovak.net/the-quest-for-a-programming-language-that-doesnt-suck-part-1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.johnnovak.net/the-quest-for-a-programming-language-that-doesnt-suck-part-1/</guid><description>[Listening to: Aglaia – Three Organic Experiences. Track #3, Seven Ancient Glaciers is a definite stand-out!]
Welcome, stranger! This series is a journal that attempts to document my trials and tribulations as I embark on the impossible journey of finding the perfect programming language that I can use with great joy on my hobby projects. An epic quest of unfathomable difficulty, indeed!
In this episode: after a somewhat lacklustre introductory meandering on the merits of the multi-language approach in software development, things get heated up quite a bit with some good old-fashioned C++ bashing, after which the hero calms down and finally sets some GOALs.</description></item></channel></rss>