<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ms-dos on Recent posts</title><link>https://blog.johnnovak.net/tags/ms-dos/</link><description>Recent content in ms-dos on Recent posts</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.johnnovak.net/tags/ms-dos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Grand MS-DOS gaming General MIDI showdown</title><link>https://blog.johnnovak.net/2023/03/05/grand-ms-dos-gaming-general-midi-showdown/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.johnnovak.net/2023/03/05/grand-ms-dos-gaming-general-midi-showdown/</guid><description>Table of contents Introduction Meet the contestants Roland Sound Canvas SC-55 Roland Sound Canvas VA Yamaha MU80 Yamaha S-YXG50 Recording process Capturing MIDI data Recording the audio Post-processing Recordings Quick impressions Final verdict Roland SC-55 vs Roland Sound Canvas VA Roland SC-55 vs later Sound Canvas models Roland SC-55 vs Yamaha MU80 Yamaha MU80 vs Yamaha S-YXG50 In closing Recordings, links &amp;amp; further reading Files Softsynths Reviews Introduction The Roland SC-55 sound module is the undisputed king of mid-late 90s General MIDI music in MS-DOS retro gaming circles.</description></item><item><title>Creating a bootable MS-DOS partition on a CF card</title><link>https://blog.johnnovak.net/2023/01/21/creating-a-bootable-ms-dos-partition-on-a-cf-card/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.johnnovak.net/2023/01/21/creating-a-bootable-ms-dos-partition-on-a-cf-card/</guid><description>The problem So you got a nice retro PC and a CompactFlash (CF) to IDE adapter, and now you want to install MS-DOS 6.22 onto a CF card to put the machine to good use (i.e., playing retro games&amp;mdash;what else, really?) But no floppy drive, no Gotek, and no CD-ROM drive. What&amp;rsquo;s a young bear to do?
In WinUAE, you can mount any physical hard disk or removable flash media for direct low-level access with a few mouse clicks, then you can partition and format it via AmigaOS running in the emulator.</description></item></channel></rss>